Finding Aid for Arthur E. Armstrong papers, 1911-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur E. Armstrong papers 1911-1938
Armstrong, Arthur E. (Arthur Edward), 1884-1976.
2 linear feet (3 boxes).
854 Aa 2
Hillsdale, Michigan, Singer Sewing Machine Company representative in central China, 1911-1917; wife, Elsa F. Armstrong of Northfield, Minnesota, Evangelical Lutheran missionary in China, 1911-1917. Correspondence between Arthur and Elsa Armstrong, Elsa Armstrong's family, and other missionaries, concerning life in China; also photographs and Arthur and Elsa Armstrong's reminiscences of China.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Philip E. Armstrong (donor no. 6098 ), October 1977.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur E. Armstrong was born in Frontier in Hillsdale County, Michigan. He graduated from Hillsdale College in 1910, then in 1911, he went to China with Underwood & Underwood Stereoptican Views. While in Hankow, he transferred over to the Singer Sewing Machine Company. It was while in China that he met his wife Elsa Bianca Felland. Elsa Felland was born in Northfield, Minnesota on March 15, 1890. She went to China in 1912 as a teacher-missionary under the auspices of the Norwegian Lutheran Church of America. She and Arthur Armstrong were married June 30, 1915. The Armstrongs remained in China until 1917 when they returned to the United States.
The Armstrong collection consists of correspondence, photographs, and other materials largely relating to the period of their stay in China. Included is the correspondence Elsa Felland exchanged with her parents, and letters exchanged between Elsa Felland and Arthur Armstrong before their marriage and in periods of separation after their marriage. These letters are useful for their discussions of missionary life and for insight into Arthur Armstrong's work with an American company in China. During part of their stay in China, Elsa Felland and Arthur Armstrong were witnesses to the 1911-1912 revolution in China.
Approximately fifty per cent of the collection consists of visual materials, primarily photographs, although there are some striking posters from the period of the Chinese revolution, 1911-1912. The photographs concern such subjects as Chinese urban life, mission activities, daily life in China, and Arthur Armstrong's work with the Singer Sewing Machine Company. The Armstrong collection also contains a large number of stereoptic card views of China, the St. Louis World's Fair, Port Arthur, the Philippine Islands, and Japan. These were probably sample cards that Armstrong sold in connection with his work with the Underwood & Underwood Company.
Subjects:
Missions--China.; Missionaries--China.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Lutheran Church--Missions--China; Armstrong, Elsa F. (Elsa Felland), 1890- .
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--History--Revolution, 1911-1912.; Felland family.; Japan.; Missionaries--China.; Missions--China.; Singer Sewing Machine Company.; Lutheran Church--Missions--China.
Contributors:
Armstrong, Elsa F. (Elsa Felland), 1890-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Posters.; Stereographs.
- Correspondence
  - Letters of Elsa B. Felland to the Felland family (Box 1)
    - Undated and 1917, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of Elsa B. Felland to Arthur E. Armstrong
    - Undated and 1913-1916, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of Arthur E. Armstrong to Elsa B. Felland
    - Undated and 1917, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters of Arthur E. Armstrong to Felland family members
    - 1914-1916 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Felland family members to Arthur E. Armstrong and Elsa B. Felland
    - Undated and 1912-1916 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Undated and 1911-1938 (Box 1)
  - Fragmentary letters (Box 1)
  - Maps and clippings (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences of Arthur E. Armstrong and Elsa B. Armstrong (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (1981 and 1983 accessions) (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - Armstrong, Ella B.: trip to China; mission scenes (Box 2)
    - Armstrong family (Box 2)
    - Chinese civil war, 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    - Chinese life scenes (Box 2)
    - Chinese urban scenes (Box 2)
    - Friends and associates in China (Box 2)
    - Mission building and churches (Box 2)
    - Singer Sewing Machine Company in China (Box 2)
    - China postcards (Box 2)
    - Color prints of Japan (Box 2)
    - Stereoptic views
      - China, 6 folders (Box 2)
      - World views, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - St. Louis World's Fair (Box 2)
      - Port Arthur (Box 2)
      - Philippine Islands (Box 2)
      - Japan (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Albums
    - Mission life, mostly Sinyang Girls' School (Box 2)
    - Chinese urban and rural life (Box 2)
    - Elsa Felland's trip to China (Box 2)
    - Chinese civil war, 1911-1912 (Box 2)
    - Shanghai and miscellaneous Chinese scenes, Singer Sewing Machine Company, funeral of Empress Dowager, Sun Yat Sen's visit to Hankow (Box 3)
  - Posters (Box 3)